Good morning.
Today's דף daf is י"ג yud gimmel and we pick up from
the very first line. אמר ליה, Amar lei, but let me reframe
what the question was. We're looking at the משנה Mishna where it
says a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh, shoteh, v'katan can do
the שחיטה shechita if they're being observed. Well, not can, if they
did it, it's okay if they're being observed and you see that
they did it technically correct. This raises the question, well, first of
all, on the one hand, it emphasizes that שחיטה shechita is more
about the physical act. It's not fundamentally about a sort of an
act of the mind, if you would,
where the fundamental principle is that חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh, shoteh, v'katan
are not בני דעת, bnei daat, which is not necessarily just describing
their intellectual ability, but saying that the law does not recognize them
as agents to effect a halakhic change, to engage in transactions, to
change status and so on. Okay, but this is fundamentally a physical
act and it's not an act of דעת. daat. Nevertheless, the גמרא
Gemara wants to know: Is it just a physical act or does
it require כוונה? kavana? כוונה kavana is different than דעת. daat. כוונה
kavana is intention, understanding, what is the act that you're doing exactly?
It's not just incidental, it's not accidental, you're trying to actually kill
the animal.
And the גמרא's Gemara first response is: Oh well, maybe שחיטה shechita
doesn't require intention. It's purely just a physical act. You don't... it
can be completely incidental. You don't even have to be aware that
you're slaughtering an animal and that's why חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh, shoteh,
v'katan are good. But then the end of that discussion, or maybe
connected but not explicitly connected, the גמרא Gemara starts to analyze: What
is exactly the ability, what is within הלכה, halakha, what is the
recognizability of a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh, shoteh, v'katan to act in
different ways? So we acknowledge that they're not בני דעת bnei daat
as I said. They cannot do something that fundamentally is about effecting
a change of status through a mental act, even though it's accompanied
by physical act. But the question is: Do they have מחשבה, machshava,
or if you will, do they have כוונה kavana when they basically
are
just to something that says that the act that they are doing
is intentional? Is that acknowledged or not? So we had just sort
of implicitly said that we assume it wasn't the case by שחיטה,
shechita, but it's okay, maybe you don't need it by שחיטה. shechita.
But now we're actually asking, maybe it would be. And the distinction
that it would be something that they could achieve, defining their actions
as intentional,
as
opposed to דעת, daat, which I just said. Okay. It's something that
one implies the other though. No.
That's why I made a distinction. So we quoted a משנה Mishna
about them making various vessels out of gourds and whatnot, and it
said
they have מעשה maaseh but they don't have מחשבה. machshava. And presumably
what that's saying is that if they've done an act to make
something into a כלי, kli, then we say that act is significant,
that actually their acts are defined as intentional acts. If, however, they
didn't do an act, it was just about their thought, so they
saw something that was hollowed out and they thought 'Oh, I want
to use that as a כלי', kli we cannot sort of acknowledge
their thought per se, but if they're doing an act, we can
define it as an intentional act. So the question is: When רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said 'Do they have thought?', the גמרא Gemara says:
Well, what do you mean? The משנה Mishna says they have an
act that's an intended act, that we acknowledge, they don't have מחשבה
machshava by itself. So what question is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asking?
So that's where we pick up. Let's take a look. And after
we see that, I'll describe a little bit more about how to
exactly frame what the two issues are and what the middle case
is. So top of י"ג עמוד א'. yud gimmel amud alef. So
אמר ליה, amar lei, so the question was asked, רבי חייא בר
אבא Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba said this was רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan
question, and רב אמי Rav Ami said: 'What type of a question
is it?'. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבי חייא בר אבא
Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba said back: 'Here's the question: מחשבה גרידתא, Machshava
gureita, if it's just about the thought, the intention let's say, not
thought maybe intention of a חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh, shoteh, v'katan, לא
קא מיבעיא ליה. lo ka mibaya lei. That was not רבי יוחנן's
Rabbi Yochanan question, because that's explicit that their thought alone, their intention
alone is not significant unless it's accompanied with an action. כי קא
מיבעיא ליה, Ki ka mibaya lei, what was רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan
question? מחשבתו ניכרת מתוך מעשיו. Machshavto nikeret mitoch maasav.
If his intention is evidenced through his action. Now how is that
different than the case of actions where we said his actions are
meaningful? So let's see the example. כגון, Kegon, for example, דהוי קיימא
עולה בדרום. d'havi kaimei olah b'darom.
Now we're switching gears completely from making vessels to slaughtering a קרבן.
korban. Let's say a קרבן עולה korban olah was in the south.
As you might remember going back to זבחים, Zevachim, a קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim and a קרבן עולה korban olah is one of them,
has to be in the north. So here was the קרבן korban
within the south. ואתיוה בצפון. Ve'asyu b'tzafon. And this חרש
שוטה וקטן, cheresh, shoteh, v'katan, you know, because they can do a
שחיטה shechita of חולין, chullin, maybe they can do a שחיטה shechita
of קדשים kodshim as long as somebody is observing them. At least
to define that the act of שחיטה shechita was correct. The problem
is is that by קדשים, kodshim, presumably it's not enough that the
animal is considered שחט, shechted, but it has to be שחט shechted
as קדשים, kodshim, שחט shechted as an עולה, olah, certainly if you
want
it to be
יוצא. yotzei. ואייתיא בצפון ve'asya bitzfon and they moved it to the
north, ושחטה veshachtah
and they slaughtered it. So מאי, mai, what do we say? מדאייתיא
בצפון ושחטה איכווין לה, mide'asya bitzfon veshachtah ichaven lah,
since he brought it to the north and slaughtered it there, we
say obviously that reveals the fact that he knew it was an
עולה olah and he slaughtered it. So we see there slaughtering it
as an עולה. olah. או דילמא o dilma or do we say
maybe not? מקום דלא איתרמי ליה, makom delo itarmi lei, maybe there
was not enough room over there in the south and he brought
it to the north. Who knows why he brought it to the
north? We really can't say. So therefore we want to know what
is the story about an action that is ניכרת מתוך מעשיו nikeret
mitoch ma'asav but not yet at the full state of action. So
how do you exactly describe this middle case? I'll first tell you
what תוספות Tosafot says because it fits much better in the description
of the גמרא Gemara and then I'll tell you what רש"י Rashi
says. תוספות Tosafot says the following. When we say they don't have
מחשבה, machshava, that means any or again מחשבה machshava I'm going to
interpret as intention, which doesn't mean that they don't intend things, it
just means הלכה halacha doesn't acknowledge it, doesn't give it weight. So
what that means is any statement of theirs, I am intending to
do this, let's take the case where they didn't have מחשבה, machshava,
I'm planning on using this hollowed out coconut as a bowl, we
say I don't really care, it doesn't mean anything, it doesn't affect
any הלכתי halachic status or whatever, we don't acknowledge that. Okay, that's
they don't have intention.
What does it mean that they have an action? It means if
regardless of what they're saying, we look at their action and it
is self-evident what its purpose is, then we say that that's a
meaningful action. So they're hollowing out a coconut, well a coconut you
don't have to hollow out, whatever, they're hollowing out a gourd, you
know, why does somebody hollow out a gourd? So it's obviously that
they're doing it, there's no question this is an action to make
it into a כלי, kli, so we say clearly it's an action
of making it into a כלי, kli, we don't have to focus
on intention, we can look at the action and say this is
an action of making it into a כלי. kli. That's they have
action. What is the middle case? The middle case is like that
last case, but there's a question, there's an element of doubt. It
probably is an action of making it a כלי, kli, but maybe
he's just trying out his new knife. You know, who knows why
he's doing it? If we're not, if it's not self-evident, is it
strong enough to say that we say that this is the right
action, the action that we need? So that's the example of the
עולה. olah. Probably
he's, it's a שחיטת עולה, shechitat olah, but there's a likelihood, there's
not a likelihood, there's a possibility that he just ran out, you
know, there it was too crowded there and he moved it here.
So it's not self-evident that it's the שחיטה shechita of an עולה,
olah, how do we define this case?
Well what about the שופר? shofar? What? And so not,
are we going to make
it, so the question is, so okay that's the way תוספות Tosafot
explains it. So again, an intention, a naked intention is immaterial, even
a stated intention during an action is immaterial, we really don't care
what you're saying, we can't acknowledge what you're saying your thoughts are,
but what we can do is focus on the action itself and
say what type of an action is it and use the context
to assess that. And the question is what if there's an element
of doubt? Now the question within תוספות Tosafot is, you know, or
if you want to just say it within the הלכה halacha here
is, what is the reason that הלכה halacha can't distinguish between when
he claims what his intention is or when he is doing an
action and we're looking at the action? One way of saying this
is that we just need evidence about what he's thinking. If he
just makes a statement, maybe we can't somehow take that as clear
enough evidence about what you're really thinking, somehow because you're a minor.
Right, like why not? Just because you're a minor, I mean if
you're saying it probably you are, but who knows? Maybe minors change
their time, their thoughts every day. I don't know. But if you
actually do something, that proves what you're thinking. That's one way of
reading תוספות. Tosafot. I have to tell you I'm not satisfied with
that for you know, well why is the action more evidence of
what you're thinking than your claim? So I'm not so happy with
that. And why would when you're making a statement during your action,
if you're also doing an action, doesn't that also weigh in? So
the alternative which I would much prefer to say is is that
it's not a question about what you're thinking, but whenever there's an
issue and this is important about כוונה kavana or even possibly לשמה
lishma by קרבנות, korbanot, the question that we always have to ask
ourselves is, if the הלכה halacha requires intention, is it requiring it
as an independent criteria or is it requiring it to define the
action? So for example, if I have to שחט shecht an animal,
an עולה לשמה, olah lishma, is it saying that there are two
הלכתי halachic requirements here for שחיטה? shechita? One is I have to
do the שחיטה shechita and the other is that at the moment
of שחיטה shechita I have to be thinking that this is an
עולה olah and that's a separate requirement that takes place at the
time of שחיטה. shechita. Or is it really no, there's a requirement
that you do a שחיטת עולה shechitat olah and the act of
a שחיטת עולה shechitat olah is defined not only physically but what
its intention is, but it's about the demand of an action. So
for example if you look at the case of let's say hollowing
out a gourd, is the idea that I have to be thinking
that I want to use it as a כלי? kli? Is that
the criteria I'm defining Meaning, and because I'm thinking about it while
I'm doing it, we know I'm thinking about it? Or no? What
we're saying is to define this as a כלי, kli, if it's
made for a כלי, kli, then that's the כלי. kli. And what
we really are concerned about is, is this an action of making
it a כלי? kli? Not we're concerned about what you're thinking per
se. We're concerned about how we're defining your action, and your thought
is only relevant to the degree that they define the action. That
I believe, that's a general question whenever there's a demand of intention.
Is it about its own criteria or about defining the action? That
I believe is why the גמרא Gemara is willing to distinguish by
a minor. It says by a minor for whatever reason, הלכה halacha
is not willing to acknowledge his intention per se. You're thinking this,
who knows what he's thinking, he's a minor, whatever. We're hard enough
to get into heads of adults, certainly to get into heads of
kids. So, who knows what you're thinking. No matter what you're saying,
we cannot give weight to the intention. But what we can do
is we can observe your action and define the type of action
it is. So it has nothing to do with what you're saying,
it has to do with looking at the action, looking at the
context, and in its own objective terms defining the action. That is,
I believe, how why the גמרא Gemara is making this distinction, and
then it says, okay, but what if there's some ambiguity about how
to define that action? But again, this is a doubly important question.
On the one hand, it's a question about what we are able
and not able to say about minors. And on the other hand,
it's a question about what is the role of כוונה. kavana. Is
the role of כוונה kavana an independent criteria, or is the role
really כוונה kavana just defining the nature of the action? So the
גמרא Gemara is saying by minors, we're not willing to give weight
to their intention, we are willing to give weight to their action
as a type of an intended action. But what if there's an
ambiguity about what the intended action is really about? Okay, so that's
how I would frame this issue. I'll take one or two questions
and then we'll go on. Yes, Dov, you had a question?
I'm not sure. Well, would you distinguish between a statement at the
time of the action itself, or statement said, yeah, what I did,
you know, five minutes ago was...
Right, so תוספות Tosafos versus ר''י, Ri, and I'll tell you what
רש''י Rashi says in a minute, is that any statements are completely
immaterial. We do not pay any attention to anything a קטן katan
is saying. Which, again, works if you say that even when he
does an action, it's not because we're getting to his thoughts, but
we're saying, we're saying for הלכה halacha we're not prepared to give
any weight or to try to give any status or significance to
the thoughts of a קטן. katan. But what we are prepared to
do is say that the actions are not completely incidental. We're able
to describe them as certain types of actions, intended actions. Now, you
might say that that's just a play of words, right, because how
can something be an intended action if you're not paying if you're
not giving, but the point is, is that we're able to describe
the action based on context and its objective criteria, you know, rather
than by having to actually care directly about what the קטן katan
was actually thinking. So according to תוספות, Tosafos, to answer your question
is no, it doesn't matter. His whole point is we ignore whatever
he's thinking or whatever he's saying he's thinking.
Yes? But according to that then, you can never say עולה לשם
חובה, olah lesheim chovah, because you have to have specific intention for
this person.
We don't know that. Oh, well, you're talking about לשם
בעלים.
lesheim
bealim. Okay, well, anyway, it's an interesting question anyway about an עולה,
olah, because as we know, if you had סתם stam intention, you
don't have negative intention, it also works. So why exactly the גמרא
Gemara says, well, why does it matter he's thinking about an עולה,
olah, right? You don't have specific intention. So as we're going to
see when we get to the next משנה, mishna, we'll get to
the end here, it might be enough just to say that he's
acknowledged that it's a קרבן. korban. It's not מתעסק. misyasek. It doesn't
really have to, you know, if he thought it was חולין, chulin,
then it wouldn't be a שחיטת קדשים. shichitas kodashim. But that's the
only thing that you need. Otherwise you don't need specific intention, you
just don't need negative intention.
So we have to say, you know, based on all we said
before, that someone had to check the knife.
Yeah,
yeah, yeah, all of the acts of שחיטה shichita were done correctly.
And we're saying that
although for קדשים, kodashim, you know, where this is
fine, we're basically trying to prove that יש לו מחשבה yesh lo
machshava then, according to this.
Well, מחשבה ניכרת מתוך מעשיו, machshava nikares mitoch ma'asav, okay, when it's
not about מחשבה machshava itself. Charlie?
I can think of examples where we require intention. I can think
of examples where we don't require intention. And it's not clear to
me what the rule is.
Well, that's a good point. In every area of הלכה halacha you
have to ask, like the גמרא Gemara did by שחיטה, shichita, do
you require כוונה kavana or not require כוונה? kavana? Sometimes you do,
sometimes you don't. What I'm saying is, even when you require כוונה,
kavana, on what basis do you require it? Because it's an independent
criteria, or because it defines the nature of the action? Okay. And
I would like to say that at least when we're making this
distinction between a קטן, katan, the logic it makes according to תוספות
Tosafos is the, you know, we don't give weight to the כוונה
kavana itself, we can define what type of an action is being
done. But that assumes that כוונה kavana is not an independent criteria.
Can he change the mind before שוחט? shocheting?
Sure. But how would we know is a good question. But, yeah,
I mean, it all depends on what's done at the time of
the action. Now, according to רש''י Rashi and then we have to
go on, רש''י Rashi says that this is all a question of
an index into what the קטן katan is thinking. רש''י Rashi says
when he doesn't have מחשבה, machshava, it means that
he
doesn't... So if he just declares what he's thinking, it doesn't matter.
If he declares what he's thinking and does an action that demonstrates
that, then we believe that that's what he's thinking. So if he
says, I want to use this gourd as a vessel, who cares?
You just said it. I want to use this gourd as a
vessel, and he's hollowing it out, then we believe you and we
say that that's really what your intending. If he says, if he
just hollows it out and doesn't say anything, that's the middle case.
Can we figure out what you're thinking just through your actions if
you didn't say anything? So for רש״י Rashi it's not as much
of a categorical distinction as תוספות. Tosafos. For רש״י Rashi it's when
do we believe that that's what you're thinking? If you say it
and do an action that backs it up, we believe it. If
you don't do an action that backs it up, we don't believe
it. If you just do the action and don't say it, then
we don't know whether or not you're really thinking it or not.
So for רש״י Rashi it's a question of really believing it's what
the קטן katan is thinking. It doesn't sound that way so much
from the words of the גמרא, Gemara, but that's at least the
way רש״י Rashi frames the issue. Yes.
What's the difference between a קטן katan and an adult?
Because an adult we believe, if you say that's what you're thinking,
we believe it is.
You're more likely to be serious.
But
somehow we say אין בהם דעת, ein bahem da'as, even though we
can say you're saying it, you're doing it, and...
No, no, no. Again, as I said before you walked in and
then we have to move on, saying that they're not בני דעת
bnei da'as does not mean that they don't have thoughts or intention
or that we even acknowledge their intention, which is what we're discussing
here. דעת Da'as is more not just the halachic ability to effect
a change of status, okay?
That's what we're talking about. Is it arbitrary? Why would we say
that? Because if he's able to do all
this...
Because the law does not recognize him yet as a full agent.
So that's what more אין בהם דעת ein bahem da'as means. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara goes on and says the following. So
that's the question: what about this middle case? So let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. And so the גמרא׳ס Gemara's response: הא
נמי אמר רבי יוחנן חדא זימנא. Ha nami amar Rabbi Yochanan chada
zimna.
So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan already addressed this middle case at a
previous time that now we taught in the משנה. Mishna. המעלה פירותיו
לגג מפני הכנימה. Hama'aleh peirosav legag mipnei ha'knima.
Somebody brought his fruit up to the roof because he was afraid
of like infestation from
whatever type of ant, bug that that is. וירד עליהם טל. Veyarad
aleihem tal. And then there was dew on them because they're exposed
and they're up on the roof. Now the הלכה halacha is that
picked fruit, harvested fruit, cannot become טמא tamei until they come in
contact with liquid. Not only until they come in contact with liquid,
but until the owner either places liquid on them or wants or
is happy that there's liquid on them. So you put them up
on the roof and the dew went on them. Now there's liquid,
but do you want there to be dew on them? Probably not.
Who wants your fruit to get wet? So it says even though
the dew fell on them and you put them on the roof,
you put them on the roof not for the dew but because
of the infestation. So they are not in the category of כי
יותן, kiyutan, which means if water is placed on any on a
fruit then it could become טמא. tamei. The phrase from the תורה,
Torah, כי יותן מים על זרע. ki yutan mayim al zera. So
to say they're not in כי יותן kiyutan means that they're not
susceptible to טומאה tumah even though water touched them because you did
not desire it, okay? אינם בכי יותן. Einam bekhiyutan. ואם נתכוון לכך,
Ve'im niskayven lekach, if you intended it, so there's כוונה kavana by
itself, they're up on the roof and you say, oh, you know
it's good, the dew will fall on them, they'll get wet, they'll
get moist, that'll be good. So pure intention, so הרי הם בכי
יותן. harei hem bekhiyutan. Then it makes the dew does make them
susceptible for טומאה. tumah. That's an adult, that pure intention matters. העלום
חרש שוטה וקטן, He'alum cheresh shoteh vekatan, if the חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh vekatan brought them up to the roof, אף על פי
שנתכוונו לכך, af al pi sheniskayvnu lekach, even though they intended this,
אינם בכי יותן, einam bekhiyutan, the dew does not affect their status,
מפני שיש להם מעשה ואין להם מחשבה. mipnei sheyesh lahem ma'aseh ve'ein
lahem machshava. Because they have an action but they don't have intention.
So according to תוספות, Tosafos, you know רש״י Rashi would just read
it whether they did or did not make a declaration. I'm not
going to repeat רש״י, Rashi, I'll say תוספות Tosafos would read it:
why is it not considered an action if they brought it up
to the roof? Because it is not an action. Remember, for תוספות
Tosafos the whole idea of the action was an action that is
self-evident. Here you are, you're bringing it up to the roof, we
even started by saying that you had an infestation, and maybe even
if you didn't have an infestation, who knows why you bring things
up to the roof? Maybe to get sun. So bringing it up
to the roof, even if it was accompanied by an intention, will
not be relevant for a minor because a minor, the only thing
that's relevant is when the act is the action and an action
that is self-evident. And that's not the case here. So for an
adult the thought is relevant, not for a minor. Okay, so that's
exactly what we said before. Now we're going to see that רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to question the middle case. ואמר רבי
יוחנן, Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said,
לא שנו אלא שלא היפך בהן. lo shanu ela shelo hipech bahen.
When is it that the חרש שוטה וקטן׳ס cheresh shoteh vekatan's actions
are relevant? When he did not turn them over. Like
let's say it was dew, this morning it dew lay on them,
and then they went over and you flipped it over. So why
the heck are you flipping it over after dew fell on it
this morning? So the only explanation is because you want dew to
fall on the other side tomorrow morning. Okay, so therefore that is
a self-evident action. So in that type of a
case רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Mean... or
oh I see.
That's a good point. Yeah, that complicates things. So then it's not
what they're thinking, it's what the owner's thinking. I think we're assuming
they are the owner. They are the owner.
Yeah, okay. But good point. That would complicate it, because then it's
not much more about what the owner is thinking. Okay. הרי זה
בכי יותן. harei zeh beki yutan. So anyway, so it says, so
you see רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is already dealing in the middle
case. Why's it a middle case? Because תוספות Tosafot said, look, at
the end of the day, although you're flipping it over, you know,
it's most likely because you want the dew to fall on the
other side, but it's not a hundred percent that way. Maybe you're
flipping it over because, again, you're afraid of infestation or because you
want it to get sun on the other side, so it's not
a hundred percent. So the גמרא Gemara understands this to be the
middle case. So again, the way תוספות Tosafot is reading is, why
is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asking about a case of an action
that's not self-evident? Isn't that what he addressed in the case of
flipping over the fruit, and he said that even that type of
an action, if it's done by a חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh
vekatan, does have halachic significance? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. הכי קמיבעיא ליה. hachi kamibaia lei. You're right, he did say
that that does have significance, but here was his question: דאורייתא או
דרבנן? de'oraisa o derabanan?
Is the only giving that action weight—is he giving that action weight,
does he believe that even at a biblical level or only at
a rabbinic level? And one relevance of whether—of the weight of it
is, would be the way רש״י Rashi says it is: is it
just to be strict or even to be lenient? So if he
says the fruit can become טמא, tamei, you're being strict, so maybe
for being strict it's דרבנן, derabanan, you'll give it significance. But when
it comes to be lenient, like for example to validate the שחיטה
shechitah of a קרבן, korban, that he'll say, I won't go by
the action unless it's self-evident. So yes, it's true רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan does give weight to this when it's this somewhat ambiguous action,
but we want to know is it just to be strict or
even to be lenient? Is it only rabbinical or even biblical? So
now the גמרא Gemara is just going to say the same question
but from reframing it, so let's take a look. רב זביד בר
יצחק מתני הכי. Rav Zevid bar Yitzchak masni hachi.
So here's the way רב זביד בר יצחק Rav Zevid bar Yitzchak
told over this discussion. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן.
Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. רבי חייא בר אבא
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba said איבעי ליה לרבי יוחנן, ibei lei leRabbi
Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asked: קטן יש לו מעשה או אין
לו מעשה? katan yesh lo ma'aseh o ein lo ma'aseh? As opposed
to the way we described it before as to if they have
intention, here we're saying—which then in the end wound up saying it
meant an action which wasn't self-evident—here we're framing it differently: does he
have an action or not an action? So אמר ליה רבי אמי,
Amar lei Rabbi Ami, so רבי אמי Rabbi Ami said: ותיבעי ליה
מחשבה. vesibei lei machshava. Why don't you ask if—if his intention is
relevant? מאי שנא מחשבה דלא קמיבעיא ליה, mai shna machshava dela kamibaia
lei, why are you not asking that? דתנן אין להם מחשבה. detnan
ein lahem machshava. The משנה Mishnah about, you know, hollowing out the
gourd says their intention alone is not significant. So מעשה נמי לא
תיבעי ליה. ma'aseh nami lo tibei lei. So you also shouldn't ask
if they have an action, דתנן detnan the same משנה Mishnah says
יש להם מעשה, yesh lahem ma'aseh, that if they have an action
of hollowing out the gourd, it is significant. So גמרא Gemara says
הכי קמיבעיא ליה. hachi kamibaia lei. Alright, that's true, but here was
his question: דאורייתא או דרבנן? de'oraisa o derabanan?
Is—is the weight of their action something that has biblical significance? And
again, would it be even lenient or only rabbinic? ופשט, ufashat, and
here was his conclusion. So here's the upshot of the whole thing:
יש להם מעשה ואפילו מדאורייתא. yesh lahem ma'aseh ve'afilu mide'oraisa. They have
an action and that has even biblical weight, so even to be
lenient. And that's when, again, following תוספות׳ס Tosafot's way of describing this,
when the action is self-evident what its intention is. אין להם מחשבה
ואפילו מדרבנן. ein lahem machshava ve'afilu miderabanan. They have no—the intention alone
is not meaningful,
even rabbinically and even to be strict.
And again now, how about the middle case: מחשבתו ניכרת מתוך מעשיו.
machshavto nikeret mitoch ma'asav.
His—his intention is—is evident through his actions. So again, the way תוספות
Tosafot says this, it's, you know, most likely evident but not self-evident;
there's some ambiguity. So that middle case, מדאורייתא אין לו, mide'oraisa ein
lo, has no weight at a biblical level. מדרבנן יש לו, miderabanan
yesh lo, does have rabbinic weight, which the way רש״י Rashi says
means that we would be strict. So the resolution is is that
this middle case does have significance at a rabbinic level, not at
a biblical, and according to רש״י, Rashi, that means we would be
strict. So again, just to summarize, this is a very central גמרא
Gemara about not only the role of a קטן, katan, but these
halachic concepts. The halachic concept of דעת, da'at, which the גמרא Gemara
is sort of, you know, is like
the—is like being ignored here, but that's a concept where חרש שוטה
וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan are categorically excluded. That's doing a certain type
of an action and agency that require—that is fundamentally about your state
of mind and about effecting a halachic change through a state of
mind, maybe accompanied with an action, but it's very much as about
your state of mind, like a transaction would be a good example
of that. Okay, that they're categorically excluded from. You have to be
an adult and an agent and a recognized בר דעת bar da'at
in order to do those types of things in הלכה. halacha. How
about things that are much more about physical realities, like doing a
שחיטה? shechitah? Well, there's some types of things that are maybe just
about physical things that have—don't even require any intention; that was a
possibility by שחיטה, shechitah, that they're certainly okay if they were correctly
observed; that's our משנה. Mishnah. What about a middle category where about
action and intention, but not about דעת? da'at? Not
about like quite... And again, the way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* explains it
is, their intention we cannot acknowledge, we can acknowledge their action as
a certain type of intended action and the question is whether it
has to be self-evident or can there even be a certain degree
of ambiguity. That's the way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says it, we can
focus on their action as an intended action but not on their
intention per se. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says the issue is that we
actually can acknowledge their intention if it's backed up by an act,
if they stated and it's backed up by an act. But we
cannot acknowledge it if it's either not backed up by an act
or there's the action without the stated intention. That's the way רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* explains it, we can only, that's the middle case, the
action without the stated intention. The only case that we can clearly
acknowledge even on the תורה Torah *Torah* level is both the stated
intention when it's then backed up with an action. So these are
how we read the questions about a קטן katan *katan*, but again,
they're not just issues of a קטן katan. *katan*, they're issues about
הלכה halacha *halakhah* criteria. One criterion called דעת da'at, *da'at*, another criterion
called כוונה kavana. *kavannah*, which is different than דעת da'at, *da'at*. And
then when you have כוונה kavana *kavannah* accompanied with an action, the
question always is, is that there two criteria, action and כוונה kavana,
*kavannah* and they're independent, or as I believe תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is
saying, it really is no, one criterion, an action, but it has
to be defined as a certain type of action, but it's not
about the כוונה kavana, *kavannah* per se. Yes, Charlie?
If a minor can do יבום *yibbum*, there shouldn't be any question
about the action of a minor being.
No, the minor doing יבום *yibbum* is like, okay, excuse the analogy
here but because it's the case in front of us, is like
the שחיטה shechita, *shechita* case. יבום *yibbum* does not require intention. Right,
the case that actually everybody titters about or whatever that's in the
is this case about where it says about a man has an
erection and accidentally falls on a woman or something if you can
imagine that physical reality, anyway, and it says.
It was like a knife flying through the air.
Right, exactly, exactly,
and it says that that would be יבום *yibbum*. So יבום *yibbum*
is about the physical action and not about the intention, which is
exactly why there's no question about a קטן katan *katan* performing it
if it's a קטן *katan* or the קטנה *ketanah* are old enough
so הלכה halacha *halakhah* recognizes that it's considered an act of sex.
Okay, but yes. Yeah.
Maybe a better case would be the case of manslaughter versus murder.
Okay.
Well right, so that's a question also about being liable for punishment
and doing מצוות mitzvot *mitzvot*, where we say that if you're not
a בר דעת bar da'at, *bar da'at* you cannot. One way, or
you cannot sort of have that to be responsible in that way
as far as the law is concerned. One way of exactly explaining
the difference between דעת da'at *da'at* and כוונה kavana *kavannah* is well
if there's cases where you can acknowledge a קטן *katan*'s intention, why
can't you acknowledge it to have weight even in these areas of
other areas where I said they're excluded or you're saying how about
liability, might have to do with sort of being aware of consequences.
Meaning if I'm trying to hollow out a gourd, or if I'm
trying to slaughter an animal or whatever, I can intend what I'm
doing. But am I fully aware of what the change means, what
the consequences are in the immediate, in the present, in the future,
and so on? So that could be why they're excluded from דעת
*da'at*, like why they can't enter into a transaction and could also
be why they're free from liability and why they're not considered to
have in terms of מצוות *mitzvot*, because that's much more about the
immediate, it also includes a broader scope and consequences.
So if we assume דעת *da'at* is this threshold issue, that if
you don't understand the consequences of your action, then then you can't
be held liable, and next is the question of your intent. Right.
So under these various formulas, and the difference of intent is the
difference between manslaughter and murder.
Oh, I see, okay.
And so under these scenarios, could a קטן *katan*, under whose scenario
can a קטן *katan* be held liable for murder as opposed to?
Well, a קטן *katan* can never be held liable for any עבירה
*aveira* because that's the whole idea of being a קטן *katan* is
that you're not yet responsible under the law. So this is not
about being personally responsible for your actions, this is about how those
actions might affect statuses of other things but it's not about pegging
responsibility on you. So while what you're saying is correct, in one
case we could basically say in one case the קטן *katan* has
committed murder but got away with murder because you can't prosecute him,
and in the other case he's committed manslaughter. So you could describe
the actions differently but in both cases he's not liable, he's not
responsible because being a קטן *katan* means you're not yet responsible, you
can't be held responsible for your actions.
So you're right, meaning what you're saying is that those, the act,
and that's a good way of showing again how כוונה *kavannah* is
not about כוונה *kavannah* in itself but in the type of act,
changing the status of the type of act that's being done. So
it would make a difference what act was performed but either way
he can't be held liable.
Okay. So let's finish up this discussion. Okay. בעי מיניה שמואל מרב
הונא *Ba'ei minei Shmuel me-Rav Huna*. So שמואל *Shmuel* asked רב הונא
*Rav Huna*, this was actually the last סוגיא *sugya* we saw in
מנחות *Menachot*. מנין *Minayin*, since we're talking about intention, מנין למתעסק בקדשים
שהוא פסול *Minayin le-mit'asek be-kodashim she-hu pasul*? How do you know that
somebody if is מתעסק mitasek? *mit'asek*, which means incidentally slaughters sacrifices? Now
what does that mean incidentally? or you're trying to again throw knives
at a wall, so it could be. רש"י Rashi, says it means
that you are not aware that you are, oh no,
I'm sorry. רש"י Rashi does say it's like throwing the knives at
the wall. You're just picking up a knife, throwing it at the
wall, and you accidentally slaughter this animal and it's a קרבן. korban.
So even though we said before that that was good for a
non-קרבן, korban, how do we know it's not good for a קרבן?
korban?
שנאמר, Shene'emar, the verse says: ושחט את בן הבקר, Veshachat et ben
habakar, that you should slaughter the cattle. שתהא שחיטה לשם בן בקר.
Shetehei shechita leshem ben bakar. It has to be שחיטה, shechita. you
have to know that you are slaughtering an animal. So although we
suggested that by the שחיטת חולין shechitat chulin you could be completely,
it's all about the physical act and completely incidental, by קדשים kodashim
you have to intend that you are slaughtering an animal. אמר ליה,
Amar leh, זו בידינו היא. zo beyadeinu hi. No, we always knew
that there was a that פסוק pasuk existed. But לאעכובי מנין, le'arkuvei
minayin, like by all things by קדשים kodashim and how do we
know that if you don't do it, it's not good? We know
it's the לכתחילה lechatchila requirement. How do we know that if even
a problem בדיעבד bedieved that if you didn't do it, it's invalid?
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, whatever it says, אמר ליה, amar leh, לרצונכם
תזבחו, lirtzonchem tizbachu, you should slaughter it that it should be for
your desire. So here he's reading not just your desire but your
intention. לדעתכם זבחו, Leda'atchem zivchu, זבחו, zivchu, זבחו. zivchu.
Anyway, slaughter it with your knowledge. So therefore, it requires intention. So
presumably what this is doing is contrasting it to what we said
before by חולין. chulin. By חולין, chulin, it could be purely the
physical act. By קדשים, kodashim, at least you require כוונה. At least
you require to know that you are doing an act of שחיטה.
shechita, So can a קטן do שחיטת קדשים? shechitat kodashim? Well, that
goes back to our question about כוונה about דעתו ניכרת מתוך מעשיו
ויש לו מעשה, da'ato nikares mitokh ma'aso veyesh lo ma'aseh, etc. And
according at least if there's something you could say that it's self-evident
that he knows through the action that he's actually slaughtering an animal,
according to רש"י that would be okay.
Because then he brought it to the north.
Right, well, that's about what he knows it's an עולה. olah. Here
it's about knowing that it's an animal. So according to רש"י, this
is about knowing you're slaughtering an animal. תוספות Tosafos, says it actually
goes further than that. תוספות Tosafot, says this is also coming to
exclude a case where you don't realize that it's a קרבן. korban.
You thought that this was חולין chulin and you just happened to
be standing around in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay, but what
about bringing to the north?
Why would you then?
Unless we're not talking about bringing to the north. We're talking about
a simple question. We're not even talking about a קטן. How do
you know somebody who is מתעסק? mitasek? What's מתעסק? So for רש"י
it means you weren't intending to slaughter at all. For תוספות Tosafot
it means even if you were intending to slaughter but you weren't
aware that it was a קרבן. korban. So that by a קרבן
korban you might have to be a שחיטת קדשים. shechitat kodashim. If
you try to make it a שחיטת חולין, shechitat chulin, then from
the perspective of קרבנות korbanot it's completely an incidental act. From the
perspective of קרבנות korbanot you have to be shechting a קרבן. korban.
Now how do you know, I don't know, maybe he says it
or maybe whatever we assume he knows it. We're not talking about
a קטן anymore. So okay. So anyway, so here we have either
way contrast with our case of חולין. chulin. חולין chulin it's possible
it's purely the physical act. By קרבנות korbanot you at least need
to do it as a שחיטה, shechita, as a שחיטה, shechita to
know you're slaughtering an animal and you might have to do it
even as a שחיטת קדשים shechitat kodashim to know you're slaughtering a
sacrifice. This guy had a question?
Not a question, just an observation that in every application of this
which is given, a person has to understand that he's giving a
גט. get. So sometimes if somebody is prone to dementia
and things, it's very problematic because the woman also has to understand
that she's being divorced.
Right, to how much, right. So those are very good points. I
would say those are different aspects. For the husband, it's exactly this
issue of דעת, not just an issue of כוונה, which I think
as we were saying before, maybe a good way of describing the
difference is it's not just intending the act but it's aware of
the consequences of the act. Right, I understand. I understand, I understand.
But as the שליח? sheliach? No. So the other point is, and
that's by the woman, because since the woman can be divorced against
her will, I mean, bracketing חרם דרבינו גרשום, Cherem de-Rabbeinu Gershom, now
she's divorced. Right, but part of, right, so part of that has
to do with her personal status as a בר דעת, the action
of receiving it. So you are correct, but to unpack that and
whether that's about כוונה, דעת, or personal status would require a much
greater discussion. But yes, these issues do play out there.
The fact they brought a פסוק pasuk here would imply that in
general, yes, you don't need to have this.
So that's what we said before. We said by חולין, chulin, even
it was completely without intention, you were playing darts.
So it should be, the same should be for just about anything
for which it's not similar.
No, no, that's the point by in הלכה halacha is that every
category has its own criteria and we have to explore each category
what its criteria are. Here the contrast was immediately to חולין. chulin.
Okay, so now that was a fascinating analysis of issues of דעת
and כוונה and minors and so on. And now we go back
to the theme of the first משנה mishna as we look at
this next משנה mishna about people and what type of people can
and cannot slaughter. And here is the next משנה mishna which was
sort of implicit all along and here it's being stated.
שחיטת עובד כוכבים Shechitat oved kochavim or שחיטת גוי, shechitat goy, נבלה
neveilah is considered not even a שחיטה shechita at all. The animal
is like it was, you know, shot in the head. It was
like it wasn't even shechted. So even if it's technically perfect, right,
the שחיטה shechita. is
in... valid ומטמא במשא. u-metamei be-massa. And because it's a נבלה, neveila,
what's one of the statuses of a נבלה? neveila? It's not just
you can't eat it, but if you touch it you become טמא,
tammei, if you carry it even without touching it you become טמא.
tammei. The animal is a pure נבלה. neveila. It's like it died
without being slaughtered because a גוי, goy, a non-Jew in הלכה halakha.
is categorically excluded, which means it's not about intention and it's not
about technically doing it correctly, that was the issues of חרש שוטה
וקטן chersh shoteh u-kattan and that we can observe. Here it's about
the fact that the תורה does not recognize a non-Jew as somebody
who can do a ritual act of שחיטה. shechita, Okay, they are
categorically excluded from the role of being a שוחט.
shochet. Okay, but wait a second. The reason why he's categorically excluded
is because we always say he has.
You could, but there are many other הלכה halacha where those are
concerns and they're not categorically excluded and therefore, so this is because
it's a categorical exclusion. Okay, so let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says, נבלה אין איסור הנאה
לא. neveila in issur hana'ah lo. So yes, you are, yes it's
a נבלה, neveila, it's not a good שחיטה, shechita but it's not
forbidden in benefit. Of course not forbidden in benefit. An animal that's
not slaughtered is not אסור assur in benefit. Ah, there's one type
of way in which an animal can be slaughtered that is forbidden
in benefit: if it's slaughtered as an act of sacrifice. So we
are not concerned that when a non-Jew slaughters an animal that he
is intending it as an act of sacrifice to his god, which
would make the animal a sacrifice to a foreign god and forbidden
in benefit. Now again, remember for us it's like, oh of course,
but remember that they are dealing in a heavily pagan world, and
the heavily pagan world where animal sacrifices are, you know, very prevalent
and everybody around you is a pagan and worships Zeus or whatever.
So if they slaughter an animal, maybe it's not crazy to think
that they're doing it as an act of sacrifice to their god.
And nevertheless the משנה mishnah is not concerned with that and they
are not forbidden in benefit. So מאן תנא, man tanna, who is
this תנא tanna that's not concerned with this? אמר רבי חייא בר
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן דלא כרבי אליעזר. amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba
amar Rabbi Yochanan de-lo ke-Rabbi Eliezer. It's not like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. דתני רבי אליעזר, de-tani Rabbi Eliezer, if it was רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, הוא אומר, hu omer, he is of the position, סתם
מחשבת עובד כוכבים לעבודה זרה. stam machshavas oveid kochavim la-avodah zarah. The,
we assume the normal thought of a non-Jew is for his idolatry.
So not like he's going around all day thinking about his idolatry,
but at least in the context of slaughtering animals, we assume that
he is going to be doing it for the sake of his
idolatry, even though interestingly, presumably he's slaughtering your animal. But who cares?
He's slaughtering your animal and in his mind he's, he's also using
a great opportunity to do an act of worship to his god.
והא נתכוין על דבר שלא שלו.
ve-ha niscaven al
davar she-lo shelo.
So he intended it on your animal.
That is not when it's through an action that change, that actually
physically changes it. Okay, okay. So,
okay, רבי אמי אמר רבי אסי, Rabbi Ami amar Rabbi Assi, הכי
קתני. hachi kattani. שחיטת, Shchitas, so he says, well maybe not, maybe,
no I'm saying not maybe not. I agree with your read of
the משנה, mishnah, I just want to even read something more into
the משנה. mishnah. Here's how to read the משנה: mishnah: שחיטת עובד
כוכבים נבלה. shechitas oveid kochavim neveila. The slaughtering of a non-Jew is
a נבלה. neveila. It's not לעבודה זרה la-avodah zarah as you said.
We don't assume a normal non-Jew is intending עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
But there is one case where it would be לעבודה זרה. la-avodah
zarah. הא דמין קאמר לעבודה זרה. ha de-min ka-amar la-avodah zarah.
I'm sorry, הא דמין קאמר לעבודה זרה. ha de-min ka-amar la-avodah zarah.
If it was the slaughtering of a מין, min, which normally is
interpreted here as heretic, but what it literally means is a Jew
that has become an idolater. So not converted, you know, on that
sort of the more medieval read that they word, read into מין.
min. It means to apostatize, to convert identity, to identify with a
different religion. But remember, you could have been a good, you know,
idol-worshipping Jew without changing your identity. It happened all the time in
the בית ראשון, bayis rishon, right? Just read the נביאים, nevi'im, that's
always what you're getting. So מין min is a Jew who is
committed to worshipping certain idols. So if that person slaughters, then we
assume that because they've actually, you know, you know, actively asserted their
worshipping of idols and broken away from this, from the Jewish requirement,
that they are constantly thinking about עבודה זרה avodah zarah and that
we would consider it to be an offering to עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. Is this a pagan priest who's, we're
talking about a Jew, we're not yet up to a non-Jew. No,
like, so that's a מין גוי, min goy, a מין עובד כוכבים.
min oveid kochavim. We'll get to that in a minute. Okay, what
about a, have a question, we'll see that in a minute. What
about a non-Jew who's really committed to עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? But
right now we're talking about a Jew. תנינא, Tanina, if that's what
the משנה mishnah is saying, then it would be teaching להא דתנו
רבנן, le-ha de-sanu rabbanan, the same thing we taught in the ברייתא.
braisa. שחיטת מין, Shechitas min, the slaughtering of a מין, min, you
know again, this Jew who is an idolater, לעבודה זרה. la-avodah zarah.
We assume it's for the sake of his idolatry and the animal
is, you can't derive benefit from the meat. פיתו, Pito, if the
bread of of such a Jew, פת כותי pas kuti is like
the bread of Samaritans, which is interesting, you would expect it to
say פת אקום, pas akum, right? The bread of, by we know
that there's a prohibition of eating the bread baked by non-Jews. We're
not going to get into now about whether it's different bread of
bakers or whatever. But it's interesting that it says the bread of
Samaritans. So if you take a quick look here at, at תוספות,
Tosafot פיתו פת כותי, pito pas kuti, he says, בפרקי דרבי אליעזר
יש, be-pirkei de-Rabbi Eliezer yesh, in the פרקי דרבי אליעזר, Pirkei de-Rabbi
Eliezer, which is, you know, an early מדרשי midrashic collection, it says,
דעזרא וזרובבל בן שאלתיאל ויהושע בן יהוצדק, de-Ezra u-Zerubbavel bin She'altiel vi-Yehoshua
bin Yehotzadak, so going back very early, at the time of
Ezra, נידו אותן בשלש מאות כהנים. niddu osan bi-shlosh me'os kohanim. ובשלוש
מאות תינוקות ובשלוש מאות ספרי תורה, u-ve-shelosh me'ot tinokot u-ve-shelosh me'ot sifrei
Torah, they put the Samaritans in חרם, cherem, והיו תוקעים ve-hayu toke'im
and they would blow the שופרות shofars to put them in חרם,
cherem, והלויים משוררים, ve-ha-Levi'im meshorerim, you get a little accompaniment of song,
ומסיימים u-mesayemim and the end of this whole story is מכאן אמרו
mikan ameru from here they said כל האוכל פת כותי כאילו אוכל
בשר חזיר. kol ha-okhel pat Kuti ke-ilu okhel besar chazir. Anybody that
eats the bread of Samaritans is like they're eating pork. Now the
reason I bring this in is it ties back to themes we
had earlier about Samaritans and about the strong antagonism between the sort
of mainstream Jews and the Samaritans and here you certainly see that
there was this whole emphasis of not just halakhically are they Jewish
or not Jewish, can you trust or not, but really creating this
strong social division through putting them in חרם, cherem, if you eat
from their bread it's like you're eating חזיר chazir dot dot dot
dot dot. So it's much more in terms of its sort of
social weight than just the rabbinic prohibition of פת עכו"ם, pat akum,
which is why here it's being framed as this פת כותי. pat
Kuti. Okay, so that's interesting in understanding the use of the word
כותי Kuti here and also the general antagonism and division that existed
between the כותים Kutim and the ישראל. Yisrael.
So they threw their bread into my pot, I throw out everything?
What, how much that goes fully halakhically or whatever, but maybe yes.
Okay, we might say that by פת עכו"ם pat akum as well.
Okay, יינו יין נסך yeino yein nesekh back to the גמרא, Gemara,
the wine is considered wine that was poured for עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, again, this is a guy that we're concerned is a regular
worshipper of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. ספריו sefarav his ספרי תורה, sifrei
Torah, even if he writes תורה נביאים וכתובים, Torah Nevi'im u-Khetuvim, ספרי
קוסמים sifrei kosemim are like books of like incantations and witchcraft, meaning
that you burn them and destroy them, they don't have any קדושה
kedushah of ספר תורה, sefer Torah, even presumably with God's name in
them. Okay, which is another interesting whole discussion about the books of
idolatry, the ספרי תורה sifrei Torah of these people, of מינים, minim,
of people that are Jews that are committed to
idolatry and פירותיו טבלים, u-ferotav tevalim, his fruits we concern is טבל,
tevel, this is a more minor point, we're concerned that he doesn't
take תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u-ma'asrot, so you have to concern yourself that
his fruit is טבל tevel and ויש אומרים, ve-yesh omerim, some say
אף בניו ממזרים, af banav mamzerim, we have to be concerned that
his children are ממזרים. mamzerim. You wonder at what stage here are
we talking about real halakhic concerns or whether this is like what
we just read by the כותי, Kuti, it's a type of a
way of using social sanctions in order to make it clear what
our lines are and who's in and who's out, like sitting שבעה
shivah when the kid's intermarried, which used to be very common. Is
that an, there's some types of questions about social
sanctions but
anyway, the
גמרא Gemara is treating this as a sober consequence of somebody who
is doing this, but one does wonder if that last stage at
least is more of a social sanction than of a real halakhic
consequence or analysis. Anyway, so now we are going to continue to
look at this issue about the slaughtering of a non-Jew and how
broad or narrow and of a מין min as well. So let's
take a look whether it is for עבודה זרה avodah zarah or
not. אמר מר, amar mar, so we're going to go back and
look at what we said before: שחיטת עובד כוכבים נבילה, shechitat oved
kokhavim neveilah,
the slaughtering of a non-Jew is a נבילה. neveilah. The גמרא Gemara
says וניחוש שמא מין הוא. ve-nechush shema min hu. This is what
Michael said: okay, you're telling me a normal
non-Jew isn't always looking for an opportunity to worship idolatry, but maybe
this guy's a really פרום frum non-Jew, that's what it means, a
מין. min. The same way a מין ישראל min Yisrael is somebody
really committed to idolatry, maybe this is a non-Jew really committed to
idolatry. Maybe he's a priest, maybe, so why aren't we concerned that
it is עבודה זרה avodah zarah even if the majority are not
that way? Let's see what the גמרא's Gemara's answer is. אמר רב
נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, well that's the question: if it's only a
minority, why should we be concerned? אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר
אבוה: amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha: אין מינים באומות עובדי
כוכבים. ein minim be-umot ovdei kokhavim. So there are not באומות עובדי
כוכבים, be-umot ovdei kokhavim, the idolaters don't have מינים, minim, don't have
people that are really committed to it. So what does that mean?
Let's see how the גמרא Gemara qualifies this. והא קחזינן דאיכא? ve-ha
ka-chazinan de-ika? What do you mean? We actually observe that there are
some of them that are really serious about it. Now also remember,
first of all, I would say two things: one is the גמרא
Gemara was written in בבל Bavel where Zoroastrianism,
which while by other גמרות Gemarot clearly assumed to be עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, it was not the type of pagan עבודה זרה avodah
zarah and so on. It didn't have idols, it didn't have images
and so on. It did believe in
a good god and a bad god, it was dualist. But anyway,
so that's one thing, but it seems that the other thing is
that in Rome and in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael under Roman
rule at this stage in history, the worship of idols was very,
very pro forma, which is why the ground was being laid. for
a monotheistic religion and Christianity and so on, you know, it was
much less frequent people that really were like deep believers, it was
much more like a type of a cultural proforma type of a
thing. So the גמרא Gemara is not just סתם stam saying these
things. There is, you know, there's certain reality in which this is
based. But the גמרא Gemara says nevertheless דהא חזינא דאיכא, de-ha chazina
de-ika, we do see that such things do exist, non-Jews that really
are committed to idolatry. So
אימא, eima, אין רוב עובדי כוכבים מינים, ein rov ovdei kochavim minim,
the majority are not. We don't need to be concerned that there
are a few that are because most non-Jews are not so committed
to it. סבר לה כי הא דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן, Savar lei ke'ha de'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi
Yochanan, and he holds like the position of רבי חייא בר אבא
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
Very important statement here applied in many many ways. נכרים שבחוץ לארץ
לאו עובדי כוכבים הם, Nochrim she-be-chutz la-aretz lav ovdei kochavim hein, non-Jews
that live outside of Israel, funny it's like what, in Israel they're
פרומער frummer but outside of Israel the non-Jews are not real idolaters.
אלא מנהג אבותיהם בידיהם, Ella min-hag avoteihen bi-yadeihen, they're just going through
the motions. They're doing the practice of their fathers. You know, it's
cultural, it's whatever, but it's not deeply religious. And therefore we don't
have to be concerned that a סתם stam non-Jew, it means every
now and then there'll be a non-Jew that's serious about it, but
we don't have to be concerned that a סתם stam non-Jew is
deeply committed to his עבודה זרה avoda zara and is doing it
for the sake of his עבודה זרה. avoda zara. And therefore the
שחיטה shchita, is נבילה neveila but it's not עבודה זרה avoda zara
and it's not אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah. מר מאיר Mar Meir
probably. Now this line is applied very liberally by the medievalists, by
תוספות, to deal with a lot of problems of dealings with Christians.
Because Christianity was assumed to be עבודה זרה avoda zara and the
question is how do we, they were, the Jewish communities were regularly
violating the laws of restrictions of interactions with עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei
avoda zara, the whole מסכת עבודה זרה, Masechet Avoda Zara, the whole
first פרק perek there. And one general response besides which I'll tell
you even a more extreme case, well not besides which but in
extreme cases they were regularly selling non-Jews, Christians, objects of worship. Okay,
so you can't just say like oh well maybe he's not really
serious, he's not going to worship his עבודה זרה. avoda zara. You're
selling them a chalice, you know, you're selling them a cross, you
can't say that they're not doing it in some type of context.
So they would, one way of dealing with that, not the only
way and not the way that sort of took the most hold,
but one way of dealing with that was quoting this line, oh
non-Jews in חוץ לארץ chutz la-aretz are not really serious about their
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Now of course it's a bizarre statement, like
that might have been, first of all, I never got the ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael versus חוץ לארץ. chutz la-aretz. I mean again the
pagans in Israel were פרומער frummer than the pagans out of Israel,
that I never got. But besides which maybe חוץ לארץ chutz la-aretz
meant outside of Rome, no I'm teasing, but anyway,
but besides which it might have been true in you know the
late period, the late Roman Empire period, that that probably was largely
true. It does not mean that it was true about Christians in
the Middle Ages. You cannot use this as an absolute truth if
it's trying to assess facts on the ground. But nevertheless it was
used as what I'll call a halakhic truth, a halakhic fiction to
deal with a lot of problematic issues relating to interactions with Christians.
Yes.
But in the Middle Ages the general level of learning and understanding
of Christians about Christianity was cathedrally low, much lower than it is
today for instance.
I mean most, most Christians in Europe, maybe 98 percent, were completely
illiterate.
Yeah, so that's in terms of sort of book knowledge but in
terms of true religious passion and commitment.
They didn't know what they were worshipping back then.
They were definitely worshipping.
I don't know, you had all these cults, you had cults of
the Virgin Mary and you had these cults of saints and so
I mean...
A lot of that was maybe based on the Christian sources.
Okay, but you're saying it's not עבודה זרה? avoda zara? I mean
it maybe would be more עבודה זרה avoda zara because it was
they were tapping into the paganism that preceded the Christian.
Exactly, they didn't know what they were doing.
What
would the גמרא Gemara say about Jews in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
how sincere, I mean most people were considered עם הארץ. am ha-aretz.
Right, yeah, so
right, right.
So you know sometimes the גמרא Gemara does say that. The phrase
that the גמרא Gemara sometimes uses
is what is it, מצות אנשים מלומדה, mitzvat anashim melumada, right, people
just do מצוות because of what we've been taught. You know we
don't do it with any intention. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara does,
it's
a common phrase,
מצות אנשים מלומדה, mitzvat anashim melumada, I'd have to find where it
says that. Okay,
so let's keep on going. Okay, obviously a very relevant גמרא Gemara
in הלכה. So let's take a look. אמר רבי יוסף בר מניומי
אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rabbi Yosef bar Minyumi amar Rav Nachman, אין
מינים באומות עובדי כוכבים. ein minim ba-umot ovdei kochavim. Now
this sounds like what we said before, but this is actually making
not a factual statement but a halakhic statement. Even if a non-Jew
appears to be a מין, min, they're not really a מין min
and it really doesn't have consequences. Now that seems like a very
strong statement, so let's see why. למאי, Le-mai, for what purpose? אילימא
לשחיטה, Ileima le-shechita, if you say that if they slaughter an animal
it's not a מין min like a priest slaughters... It's not considered
לעבודה זרה. lavoda zara. השתא שחיטת מין דישראל אמרת אסורה, hashta shchitas
min d'Yisrael amarta asura, if a Jew who becomes an idolater, it's
considered to when he slaughters an animal, it's considered to be for
the sake of idolatry. עובדי כוכבים מיבעיא? ovdei kochavim mibaya? Not a
normal non-Jew, a non-Jew who's a מין, min, a non-Jew who's a
really committed, who's a priest, you're telling me that that's not for
עבודה זרה? avoda zara? Certainly it would be and the meat should
be forbidden. אלא למורידין. ella l'moridin. Okay for the other הלכה about
whether you're supposed to try to kill them. So which is this
other area, right? What do you do with מינים? minim? You try
to kill them.
השתא דישראל מורידין, hashta d'Yisrael moridin, well, if we try to
throw the Jews,
yes, throwing them into the pit. If we try to throw the
Jew who's a מין min into the pit, עובדי כוכבים מיבעיא, ovdei
kochavim mibaya, of course we would try to do the same to
a non-Jew. So again, the גמרא Gemara it really does sound like
what he is saying, it sounds like he actually really meant it.
You know, it's sort of like the flip, if you would, about
like בעלי תשובה, baalei teshuva, that, not בעלי תשובה, baalei teshuva, well,
could be about גירים. geirim. You know, there's a גמרא Gemara that's
a very problematic גמרא Gemara that says גירים geirim are as difficult
to Israel as a scab. So תוספות quotes a statement by רב
אברהם הגר, Rav Avraham HaGer, interesting choice, who said what does it
mean? It means that the naturally born Jews hate the גר ger
because the גירים geirim are so passionate and committed about every detail
and every מצווה, mitzvah, they drive them crazy, you know? Get a.
So here you know you could say the same thing. A Jew
who becomes an עובד עבודה זרה, oved avoda zara, he's a real
believer. So he may be as much more doing things לעבודה זרה
l'avoda zara than a priest. So that would probably go back, that
could be the original intention of that statement that yes, a Jew
who's a מין min is more committed and more serious about it
than even a non-Jew who's a מין. min. But the גמרא Gemara
is not willing to say that. It says if it's, we obviously
would give the same, you know, it would be a קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. So if a Jew שחט לעבודה זרה, shacht l'avoda zara,
a non-Jew who is a מין min also שחט לעבודה זרה. shacht
l'avoda zara. So for what relevance is this statement? So אמר רב
עוקבא בר חמא Amar Rav Ukva bar Chama לקבל מהם קרבן, likabel
mehem korban, oh, for a very narrow issue whether you can accept
a sacrifice from a non-Jew who is a מין min as opposed
to a Jew who is a מין. min. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, braita, מכם. mikem. It says if a person brings
from you, ולא כולכם, v'lo kulchem, not every person can bring a
קרבן. korban. להוציא את המומר, l'hotzi et hamumar, to exclude, like we
had this before, to exclude somebody who's a מומר mumar who's basically
committed general sins. A general sinner can't bring a קרבן korban in
the area of the that the person is a general sinner. But
it also means that if a person is a מין, min, is
an idolater, we can't accept the קרבן korban if he's a Jew.
But it also says מכם, mikem, from you the Jews, בכם חלקתי,
bachem chalakti, amongst Jews I have distinguished between are you an idolater
or not, ולא בעובדי כוכבים, v'lo b'ovdei kochavim, not by non-Jews. So
non-Jews even if they're idolaters and committed to it, they can bring
קרבנות. korbanot. מאי? mai? How do you know? דילמא הכי קאמר, dilma
hachi ka'amar, maybe the verse says
this? מישראל, m'Yisrael, מצדיקי קבל מרשיעי לא תקבל, m'tzaddiki kabel m'rshiei lo
tikabel, take from the righteous don't take from the wicked. אבל בעובדי
כוכבים, aval b'ovdei kochavim, maybe it's saying by non-Jews, כלל כלל לא,
klal klal lo, don't take any sacrifices. No, לא סלקא דעתך, lo
salka datach, that doesn't make sense. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braita, איש, ish, if a person brings a קרבן, korban, מה
תלמוד לומר איש איש, mah talmud lomar ish ish, why does the
פסוק pasuk repeat it, any person? לרבות עובדי כוכבים l'rabot ovdei kochavim
to include non-Jews, שנודרים נדרים ונדבות כישראל, shenodrim nedarim u'nedavot k'Yisrael, they
can give free-will sacrifices like Jews. So non-Jews can give and actually
without any distinctions. Even a non-Jew that's a committed idolater can bring
a קרבן, korban, whereas Jews if you're a committed idolater then obviously
you've got some learning to do and some תשובה teshuva to do
before you can be bringing a קרבן. korban. So it's within this
narrow issue of bringing a קרבן, korban, not willing to fully embrace
the possibility that a Jew who's a מין min is actually more
sincere and more passionate and more problematic than a non-Jew who's a
מין. min. That the גמרא Gemara is not willing to say. So
anyway, this becomes a very relevant גמרא. Gemara. Number one, a non-Jew
is categorically excluded, but with in terms of the act of שחיטה,
shchita but it does not mean that it's לעבודה זרה. l'avoda zara.
We don't assume that normally non-Jews are doing things לעבודה זרה. l'avoda
zara. And that gets to this statement about non-Jews in חוץ לארץ
chutz l'aretz are doing things more out of habit and rote, which
might have been true in pagan Rome or whatever, but late Rome,
but then gets used in very important ways by medievalists, by the
תוספות etc. in terms of issues of Christianity. And then finally the
point that that doesn't mean it never occurs, a Jew who's an
idolater or a non-Jew who's a מין, min, then we do say
it's לעבודה זרה, l'avoda zara, which then led to questions about like
selling objects of worship to the priests, not just to the commoners,
and that also became a whole discussion in the middle ages.
But then we just reinterpreted what we were just doing. Okay let's
just now finish through the משנה. Mishnah. ומטמא במשא, u'metamei b'massa, so
this נבילה nevela causes טומאה tumah if you carry it. פשיטא, pshita,
of course, כיון דנבילה היא מטמא במשא, keivan d'nevela hi metama b'massa,
since it's a נבילה nevela of course it conducts טומאה tumah when
you carry it. אמר רבא הכי קתני, Amar Rava hachi katani, this
is what it means: זו מטמא במשא, zu metamei b'massa, this, the
שחיטה of a non-Jew causes טומאה tumah by carrying because it's a
נבילה, nevela, ויש לך אחרת שהיא מטמאה אפילו באהל, v'yesh lacha acheres
she'hi metama afilu b'ohel, and you have a worse case that causes
טומאה tumah even in a tent, meaning even if you're under the
same roof. ואיזו, v'eizu, what would that be? זו תקרובת עבודת כוכבים.
zu tikrovet avodat kochavim. If it were not if it were not
as we were saying just the slaughtering of a non-Jew but if
it actually was a sacrificial an idolatrous sacrifice then it would conduct
טומאה tumah to anything under the roof not just through carrying. וכרבי
יהודה בן בתירא u'kRebbi Yehuda Ben Besera like רבי יהודה בן בתירא
Rebbi Yehuda Ben Besera who we'll quote in a minute. איכא דאמרי
ika d'amri others say אמר רבא הכי קתני Amar Rava hachi katani
this is how we read it. זו מטמא במשא zo metame b'massa
this causes טומאה tumah by carrying ויש לך אחרת שהיא כזו v'yesh
lacha acheres shehi k'zo and you have another case analogous to this
which is just like this שמטמא במשא shemetame b'massa that only causes
טומאה tumah by carrying ואינו מטמא באוהל v'eino metame b'ohel and not
underneath a tent. ואיזו v'eiza what is that? זו תקרובת עבודת כוכבים
zu tikrovas avodas kochavim again same case something offered at to the
to gods to as an act of idolatry ודלא כרבי יהודה בן
בתירא u'dlo k'Rebbi Yehuda Ben Besera not like רבי יהודה בן בתירא.
Rebbi Yehuda Ben Besera. Meaning there's a debate as we're going to
see what is the טומאה tumah status of something that is offered
as a as a sacrifice to the gods to idolatry. We know
that you can't derive benefit does it have more severe טומאה tumah
status and that's the debate. דתניא d'tanya as we taught in the
ברייתא braisa רבי יהודה בן בתירא אומר Rebbi Yehuda Ben Besera omer
רבי יהודה בן בתירא Rebbi Yehuda Ben Besera says מניין לתקרובת עבודת
כוכבים שהיא מטמא באוהל minayin litikrovas avodas kochavim shehi metame b'ohel how
do you know that a sacrifice to עבודת כוכבים avodas kochavim causes
טומאה tumah even under the same roof? שנאמר shenaemar the verse says
ויצמדו לבעל פעור vayitzmdu l'baal pe'or they cleaved themselves to בעל פעור
baal pe'or you see this week's פרשה parsha ויאכלו זבחי מתים vayochlu
zivchei meisim and they ate the sacrifices of the dead. So why
are you comparing sacrifices to foreign gods to sacrifices of the dead?
For the following purpose. מה מת מטמא באוהל אף תקרובת עבודת כוכבים
מטמא באוהל ma meis metame b'ohel af tikrovas avodas kochavim metame b'ohel
the same way a corpse causes טומאה tumah in a tent so
too an offering to the gods and therefore how do you read
the משנה mishnah that this the slaughtering of a non-Jew causes טומאה
tumah by carrying would it mean that the slaughtering to עבודה זרה
avodah zarah is worse or the same in terms of טומאה tumah
that's open for interpretation in terms of whether or not we rule
like רבי יהודה בן בתירא. Rebbi Yehuda Ben Besera. Okay we will
end here. Just a little short of finishing the דף. daf.
Okay
this is a good place to stop. Good place to stop. End
of the משנה. mishnah.
Tomorrow same
time
tomorrow? Yeah regular time.
יישר כח shkoyach to everyone. No rabbi I said before I understand
that you can arbitrarily